Hi! I'm Uncle Bob
and this is Clean Code
Segment 1: Overview
Welcome, welcome to Episode 8 of Clean Code
the first in a series of episodes about the
SOLID principles.
Come on in, come on in.
In Episode 7 we discussed use cases, architecture
and high level design.
Many of the SOLID principles were silent
players in that episode:
we used them, but we didn't name them.
In that episode we learned that the architecture
is the shape that a system adopts in
order to meet its use cases.
We learned what use cases are and what they're not
and we learned that they should be visible
at the highest levels of the system.
We learned that while MVC may be an excelent
architecture for user interfaces,
it's not a particularly good application architecture
and should not be visible at the highest
levels of the system.
We learned that user interfaces,
databases and frameworks
are details to be hidden, they're not the central
abstractions of our architecture.
We should think of them as plugins to the application;
plugins that can be quickly and easily changed.
We learned that we can achieve this goal by creating
boundaries that separate our application from external details,
like the database, the user interface or frameworks.
And then we manage the source code dependencies
to cross those boundaries,
so they all cross in a single direction,
pointing towards the application.
In short: we learned that details should
depend in high level policies,
high level policies should never depend upon details.
That statement is actually one of the SOLID principles:
the Dependency Inversion Principle.
We should be learning about it in an upcoming episode.
Finally we learned that successful architectures allow us
to defer decisions about user interfaces, databases
and frameworks for as long as possible.
A good architecture maximizes the
number of decisions not made.
In this episode we are going to lay the foundations
for the SOLID principles
by studying the old issue of code rot that
we explored in Episode 1
but this time we are gonna do it in a lot more detail.
We'll talk about why code rots, the form that rot takes,
and the mechanisms behind that rot.
We'll discuss the symptoms of rot, and the cost of that rot
to the project, and to the enterprise as a whole.
We'll talk about what software design is
and the best ways to represent it.
We'll discuss the roles that UML and source code play
in the proper expression of software design.
We'll identify a set of design smells, symptoms of
bad design that all developers should know.
We'll do a deep dive into the history of Object Orientation,
we'll create an unambiguous definition of what Object Oriented means,
and we'll show how OO is really all about managing dependencies.
Finally we're going to study dependency management,
and we'll look at how the SOLID principles
helps us keep all the source code dependencies
in the software system under control.
So, lock and load brothers and sisters, because we're about
to storm the outer gates of the SOLID principles!
Segment 2: Special Relativity
In 1905 Einstein showed that Galileo's ship of relativity
could safely sail on Maxwell's electromagnetic waves
if we assume that the speed of light is constant
to all frames of references.
But what precisely does that mean?
It means that no matter how fast you are going
relative to the source of a light wave
you will measure the speed of that light wave relative
to YOU, at 299,792,458 meters per second.
Let's say that you've got a device that can measure
the speed of a light beam as it passes you.
Let's say you also have a flashlight. Take that flashlight,
point it to your device
and it will measure the speed of that light at
299,792,458 meters per second.
Now get onto some railroad tracks, stand in front of a train
as it's barreling down at you at 100 meters per second
Use your device to measure the speed of the light from
its headlamp as it comes towards you.
Your device will read 299,792,458 meters per second.
Now jump out of the way as the train passes
and get back on the tracks
and measure the speed of the tail light as the trains
runs away from you at 100 meters per second
and your device will read 299,792,458 meters per second.
You can repeat this experiment as often as you like. You can
do it in a car, you can do it in a jet plain or a rocket ship.
You can use the Earth whipping around the Sun or
the Sun plowing to the galaxy: it doesn't matter:
every light beam you measure, regardless of how fast
the source of that light beam is moving
will move relative to you at 299,792,458 meters per second.
And every other observer who measures those light rays
regardless of how fast they are moving relative to you
will measure them moving at 299,792,458 meters per
second relative to them.
When a light ray passes you, it's going at 299,792,458
meters per second, no matter what.
Now imagine that I have a clock.
This clock is constructed out of a tube,
with mirrors at either end.
There's a beam of light bouncing back and forth
the two mirrors.
The clock ticks every time the beam of light
hits one of the mirrors.
If the tube is 12 inches tall, then the clock ticks at
the rate of once per nanosecond.
Imagine that both you and I have such a clock
You are in one spaceship, and I'm in another. We are
both moving fast, you are moving towards me.
From my point of view, I'm stationary.
I look at my clock, and it's ticking at one tick
per nanosecond as usual.
But your clock... your clock is moving relative to me.
The light beam must move in an angle in order
to hit the two mirrors.
That means the light beam is moving along a distance
and so your clock ticks slower than mine.
You don't see that at all.
From your point of view, you're stationary
and I'm moving.
You look at your clock and you see the light bouncing
at one tick per nanosecond.
But when you look at my clock you see the light beam
moving in that zig-zag pattern,
taking longer than one nanosecond per tick.
From my point of view, your clock (and therefore
your time) are running slow.
From your point of view, my clock (and my time)
are running slow.
How slow?
Well, by applying the Pythagorean theorem
it's pretty easy to show that I will see your time
running slower by a factor of
the square root of 1 minus your velocity squared
divided by the speed of light squared.
This is a factor often called tau.
As you fly overhead, I hold up a foot long ruler
parallel to your trajectory,
I count the number of ticks that occur on my
clock as the nose of your ship
passes from one end of the ruler to the other.
You do the same, counting the ticks on your clock,
but you count fewer ticks than I do
and therefore you believe my ruler is shorter
than it actually is, by a factor of tau.
As we pass each other, our rear stabilizer fins
bump into each other ever so slightly giving us both
a nudge in a perpendicular direction.
Momentum should be conserved, so when I look at your ship
I should measure your perpendicular velocity equal to mine.
But since I perceived your time is running slowly,
I see your perpendicular velocity is too slow by a factor of tau.
The only conclusion I can come to is that your mass has
increased by an identical factor.
Remarkable, isn't it?
All these counter-intuitive effects simply by assuming that
the speed of light is constant to all frames of reference.
And these effects have experimentally verified
to n-th decimal places of accuracy.
The world is truly a very bizarre place.
And we haven't even talk about General Relativity yet.
Segment 3: The Source Code is the Design
In 1992 Jack Reeves published the landmark paper
entitled "What is Software Design?"
This paper was so important that I republished it in
my "Agile Principles, Patterns and Practices" books.
You can find that paper there, or in the URL
that's on your screen.
In this paper Jack makes this truly beautiful point:
Question: "What do Engineers produce?"
Answers: "Engineers produce documents that
specify how to build products".
Architects and building architects produce
documents, blueprints, building diagrams
that specify how to build the building.
Electronics engineers produce documents, circuit
diagrams that specify how to build the circuit board.
Mechanical engineers produce documents, mechanical
drawings that specify how to build machines.
So what in the software world would qualify
as such an engineering document?
The answer is obvious: the only document produced by
software engineers that is detailed enough to
fully specify the software product, is the source code.
OK, I hear you out there. You are saying that the
source code is the product.
No, it's not. The running program is the true product:
the binary executable is the true product.
The source code is the document from which the true product
(the running program) derives.
Let's look at this differently:
If I had an automated factory capable of building houses, then
the input to that factory would be the architect's blueprints.
If I had an automated factory capable of building circuit boards,
then the input to that factory would be the diagrams
and specifications created by electronics engineers.
If I had an automated factory capable of
building mechanical components,
then the input to that factory would be the drawings
created by the mechanical engineers.
And it turns out that I do have an automated
factory that can build a software product,
it's called "a compiler", and the input to that
factory is source code.
Therefore, the source code is the design.
Any other documents you might produce that
are preliminary to the source code
are just that: preliminary. They're not the design.
If you draw UML diagrams to help you
organize your thoughts
these diagrams are not the design. Are just preliminary
diagrams that help you create the real design.
There's nothing wrong with drawing them. They can be
very useful, but the diagrams are not the design.
The source code is the design.
And this leaves us to a very interesting conclusion:
when we build a house, we spend a great deal of
time up front designing it
because the cost of designing it is far less
expensive than the cost of building it.
When we build circuit boards we spend a lot of
time up front designing it
because the cost of designing them it is much cheaper
than the cost of building and mass producing it.
When we build mechanical components like gears
or ladders or things like that
we spend a lot of time on the mechanical design
because design is cheap
compared to cutting dies and milling metal.
And in all three of these cases, the cost of correcting errors
after design is completed and production has begun is enormous.
And so you spend a great deal of time up front on design
in order to minimize the cost of building.
But in software reverse is true:
it's far cheaper to build the product than it is to design it.
And fixing errors prior to release, that's very cheap too.
In fact, even after release, the cost of fixing errors is
far cheaper than changing the foundations of a house.
For software, the cost of building is the cost of
compiling and testing.
I can compile a million line application in seconds.
I can test it in minutes, and fixing problems
within it could take a mater of hours.
So for software the cost of building is cheap.
On the other hand, the cost of designing that
software is actually very high.
Software developers make pretty good salaries,
and the amount of code they write per hour,
or per day, it's really small.
So the costs structure is completely inverted:
the cost of design is expensive whereas
the cost of building is cheap.
And this inversion of costs means that
the strategy for building software is entirely
different from the strategy of building a house.
What if the cost of building a house was tiny?
What if you could build the whole house for
a hundred dollars and it will only take an hour?
And what if every change you made to that house
cost a hundred dollars, and took an hour?
How would you go about building such a house?
Would you hire an architect and pay him a small
fortune to create the entire design of the house
and then build the whole house at once?
Of course you wouldn't.
If it only cost you a hundred dollars and
an hour to build a house,
what you do instead is sketch a couple
of rooms on the back of a napkin
and build them and see what they look like.
Then you'd walk through those rooms
looking for things that you didn't like
and you'd make a list of those things, and then
you'd spend another hundred dollars
and another hour fixing those things.
And of course you'd continue to do that
for several more days
you'd continue by tweaking the size of the rooms, adding
new rooms adjusting the relationships between them.
Eventually you would evolve the building into the
structure you thought you could live in,
and then you'd move in.
But of course you wouldn't stop there: everyday you'd
be finding things about the house you didn't like
or you'd think of new rooms you needed to add,
you'd make a list of these things,
and then at the end of every week you'd spend another hour
and another hundred dollars making all those changes.
And you'd never stop doing that.
Oh, you might slow down to one change a week or
one change a month, or even one change a year,
but you'd never stop fiddling around with
the design of that house.
That's software for you.
It's crazy to spend a lot of time in up front design
when you can get something working quickly, and then
evolve it into a system that meets your needs.
And therein lies the rub. For when you evolve
the design of a system,
there is no guarantee whatever that you'll design it well.
It's easy to evolve the design into something that works.
Unfortunately it's also easy to make it hard to modify,
hard to maintain, unstable, crashable.
Some people call this "A Big Ball of Mud".
In Episode 6 we learned that a good suite of tests eliminates
fear and allows us to keep our code constantly clean.
So to avoid that "Big Ball of Mud", we need to practice TDD,
and apply lots of effort to keep our code continuously clean.
The problem is that in order to clean our designs, we need
to be able to recognize when those designs are going bad.
We need to know what bad design smells like.
Segment 4: Design Smells
What does bad design smell like?
What are the symptoms of bad design? And what are
the situations that a good designer should avoid?
Back in Episode 1 we studied the design smells of
rigidity, fragility and immobility.
We're going to look at those smells again in more detail,
and we'll add a few more smells on top of it.
Rigidity
Rigidity is the tendency of a system to be hard to change
What makes a system hard to change?
A system is hard to change when the
cost of making a change is high.
For example, if by making a small change I've to do
a major rebuild then that system is rigid.
Now, let's say that you have a system that
requires three hours to build and test.
Let's also say that the most minor change to the most
insignificant subsystem in that system
requires you to do a three hours build and test.
That system is rigid.
What makes that system rigid?
Two things:
First, it takes a long time to do a test and build,
and secondly, it's just a tiny change that
forces a total rebuild.
If we can reduce the build and test time dramatically,
we can make the system much less rigid,
and much easier to change.
If we could find a way to restructure the system,
such that when you change it you didn't have to
retest and rebuild the whole thing,
then changes would be a lot easier to make,
and the system would be much less rigid.
We'll talk about long-running tests in another episode.
In general, however, when a test takes a long time to run,
it's a good indication that the developers have been careless.
Long build times are a function of coupling,
this is specially true in C++ where the build time is
proportional to the number of coupled modules squared.
But again, this is something we're going to be
talking about in an upcoming episode.
When small changes forces a rebuild is
also a symptom of high coupling.
When modules are coupled, tiny little changes
causes the whole system to rebuild.
Therefore, one of our design goals is to manage
the dependencies between modules,
to ensure that when one module changes,
the others remain unaffected.
Fragility
A system is fragile when a small change to one module
causes other unrelated modules to misbehave.
Imagine the software that controls an automobile.
That software will be fragile if when you fixed
a bug with the radio it affected the electric windows.
These kinds of long-distance behavioral
dependencies are very scary.
Specially to managers and customers who viewed them
as indications of significant incompetence.
After all, if every time developers fix
a bug or add a new feature
something completely unrelated breaks or crushes,
the only conclusion you can come to, is that these
developers has lost control of the software,
and don't know what the hell they are doing.
The more this happens, the more uneasy
managers and customers become.
In the end, they'll simply freeze development,
and official rigidity will set in.
Long distance sensitivity like this is always caused by strange
couplings and dependencies sneaking across the system.
The solution is to manage the dependencies between
the modules, and isolate them from each other.
Immobility
A system is immobile, when it's internal components cannot
be easily extracted an reused in new environments.
Consider for example a system in which there is
a typical user and password login module.
If you can't quickly extract that login module
and use it in an entirely different system,
that module is immobile: it can't be moved.
Immobility is caused by couplings and dependencies
in the modules of the system,
For example let's say that I've got a login module that used
a particular database schema and a particular UI scheme
I would not be able to reuse that login
module in a different system
if it have a different database schema
and a different UI scheme.
That login module will be immobile.
The strategy for avoiding immobility
is precisely the kind of architecture that we explored in Episode 7
one that decouples the central abstractions of the application
from the database, the UI and the frameworks.
Viscosity
A system is viscous, when necessary operations like
building and testing are difficult to perform,
and take a long time to execute.
A development environment where check-ins, check-outs and
merges are long and arduous processes is viscous,
because the cost of those essential operations is high.
System designs in which new features must be
added across multiple layers of the system,
dealing with multiple transport mechanisms,
serializations, marshaling, hydrations,
this is always viscous, because even
the simplest change is costly to make.
The cause of viscosity is always the same:
irresponsible tolerance.
Developers tolerate conditions that they know
to be bad, and do nothing to correct them.
The cost of those bad behaviors is coupling.
Tight coupling makes systems hard to build,
hard to test, and hard to change.
It is that tight coupling that makes the cost
of those essential operations high.
The cure for viscosity is to attack the symptoms,
decoupling the modules and then managing
the dependencies that remain.
Needless Complexity
A real common issue in software design
discussions is how to deal with the future:
Should we design our system for
today's requirements only?
Or should we take the long view, and anticipate
all the future requirements of the system?
In other words: should we "put the hooks in" for
future extensions, or not?
Systems that carry a lot of anticipatory design
are needlessly complex.
Each hook, each extension point is another
weight added to the system
that the developers must carry in the present.
When you're afraid of your code and you think
it's hard and expensive to change,
then you're going to litter that code with
all kind of anticipatory design elements
so you do not have to change the design later.
If, on the other hand, you follow
the advice given in Episode 6
and maintain a comprehensive suite of tests
then you won't be afraid to change the code.
You won't have to litter it with a whole bunch
of anticipatory design elements.
Your designs will be simpler, easier to maintain,
and they won't be needlessly complex.
Needless complexity often leads to tight coupling
because we anticipate the future need for relationships
between modules that are not currently related.
The more such future relationships we anticipate,
the more tightly coupled the software becomes now.
The solution, of course, is to keep your design
focused on the current suite of requirements
while maintaining a comprehensive suite of tests,
that reduces your fear of changing the design later.
Of course nobody starts out to design
a system that smells bad.
Smells accumulate over time. They're caused
by a sequence of bad decisions
that are motivated by carelessness,
fear, and false experience.
The greater the mess, the harder it is to make progress
(everything gets more and more difficult)
and the greater the temptation to take the
kind of shortcuts that increase the mess.
Let's see how this happens. Let's watch some code rot.
Segment 5: Code Rot
Monday morning your boss calls you into
a conference room and then he says...
So I called you in here because
I've got a new project for you
OK
What I'd like you to do is write a program that
copies characters from the keyboard to the printer.
Mhm... alright. Anything else?
No, no. That's about it. How long do
you think that's gonna take you?
[I think this is about six lines of code]
Three weeks.
Excellent. Let's get started.
Three week is the minimum estimate where you work.
If anybody gives an estimate less than three weeks is taken
out back and suddenly beaten by the other programmers.
The reason your boss went away happy is
he got the minimum estimate.
The first thing you do is draw a diagram because, as you know,
all programmers draw diagrams before they write code.
The Copy module contains all the high level policy.
It contains the main loop that gets characters from the
Keyboard reader and sends them to the Printer writer.
It also recognizes the end-of-file condition and exits.
This diagram looks good, and you're about
to write the code that matches it,
but your boss walks in with a new guy that you've got
to orient today, and you've got to show him the ropes.
And it takes all day long. So that's gonna
pretty much eat all Monday.
Tuesday, you write the code. It looks like this.
It's the six lines you had in your head.
A simple loop that terminates on EOF, and otherwise
copies characters from the keyboard to the printer.
You're about to compile it when you realize you're late
for a quality meeting that's gonna take all day.
Wednesday you compile the code;
and it compiles right away too.
That's a good thing because right after that the
field service manager rushes into the cubicle
with a horrible bug in the field. You gonna have to
go fix it. It's gonna take you all day.
Thursday you test the code, and it works
first time your run it too.
Good thing because your boss comes in and holds you
into some horrible cross functional meeting
that's gonna take all day long.
Friday. No meetings. No bugs. No interruptions.
And it's a good thing too, because it takes all day long to
get this code into the source code control system.
Woah! You're done with two weeks to spare.
But don't let your boss know that you're done early.
You better keep busy with other stuff,
and then you can release it on time.
You win awards for this software!
Hundreds of other programmers start
using it in their systems.
It's so successful. Those six lines of code may be the most
successful lines of code ever written at your company.
Version Two
A few months later your boss comes to you and says:
So you know, that program you wrote. That copy program?
Yap.
Great work! And you're gonna see our
appreciation in your next salary review.
So, now what we'd like is for it to read from
the paper tape reader.
That's it? Just read from the paper tape reader?
Sometimes. Sometimes from the keyboard,
sometimes from the paper tape reader.
OK.
How long do you think it's gonna take you to do?
Hmmm... this sounds like a boolean and an if statement.
Three weeks.
Good! Let's get started on that!
So now you modify the diagram to show the new
dependency upon the paper tape reader.
So how should you modify this program?
You could pass a boolean into the copy program.
But that changes the signature of the function,
and all those other hundreds of programmers
that use your function
are going to have to recompile and re-test if you do that,
so they'll come to your cubicle with clubs.
No, it's probably better to use a global.
It's a simple idea: if someone wants to copy
from the paper tape reader
they'll just set the GptFlag variable to true,
and they'll call copy.
They'd better remember to clear that flag when they're done,
otherwise the next caller will get a surprise.
You can cover your butt with an
appropriate comment, like so.
// Remember to clear!
OK, so now we've to make this work.
The best feature of the C-family of languages
is the ternary operator:
it allows you to put whole if statements
into a single expression.
So we'll just insert it into the program
like so and... voilà!
Version Three
A few months later, your boss asks to see you again.
You know that copy program you wrote?
Yeah.
Sometimes, we'd like to write to the paper tape punch.
(Mmm... I've got a design pattern for this now,
I know how to solve it.)
Three weeks.
Great!
One more addition to the diagram, adding yet another
dependency to the copy module.
The change to the code is simple: just one more
global right here. You can reuse the comment.
And now you can add another ternary operator just like so.
There. That'll work. Ship it!
Summary
This code is rotting.
It's pretty clear that your boss is keep coming back
to you with more and more changes
He'll want to read from the optical character reader
and write to the synthesizer. There'll be no end to it.
And so that module will grow, and rot,
and fester, and degrade.
A few years from now it'll be time to polish off your resume
and leave that mess to somebody else.
What is OO?
Of course it didn't have to be this way.
We could have written the code like this.
Yes, this looks just like the original six lines.
But there's a small difference.
Instead of reading from the keyboard reader,
and writing to the printer writer
we're reading from getchar, and writing to putchar.
getchar reads from standard input,
which defaults to the keyboard.
putchar writes to standard output,
which defaults to the printer.
So, this version does exactly
what the previous version did.
However, standard input and standard output
can be redirected to other devices
like the paper tape reader and the paper tape punch.
This means that when your boss says:
Sometimes we need it to read from the paper tape reader.
You've got an option. You could say:
Three weeks.
Or you could tell him that it already does read
from the paper tape reader.
This code differs from the previous code by two words,
and yet those two words somehow prevent the code
from rotting when you add new devices.
In fact adding new devices, you don't
even have to recompile it!
Just what's so special about these two words?
How do they so completely change the
maintenance characteristics of this module
and utterly stopped this code from rotting?
Dependency Inversion
To understand why those two words are so important,
let's look at the diagrams again.
Here is the diagram of the first solution:
The copy module depends on the keyboard and the printer.
Look at the direction of those arrows:
the module that contains the high level policy
depends on the low level details.
And when we added new devices like the paper tape
reader and the paper tape punch,
we had to add new dependencies to the copy module
so the fan-out of the copy module grew with each change.
But now look at the diagram for the new version:
Copy depends upon getchar and putchar, but does not depend
upon the keyboard and printer.
What is it that fills the gap between those two?
It turns out that getchar and putchar are part of the
unix abstraction known as "file".
This abstraction is represented by a data structure that,
among other things, contains a table of five pointers to functions.
Those functions are: open, close, read, write and seek.
The IO drivers for the keyboard, printer, paper tape reader
and paper tape punch implement those five functions.
so when you redirect standard input and standard output
what you are really doing is loading those five
functions into the file abstraction.
That means that the IO drivers depend
on the File abstraction.
Now, look at these two diagrams side by side.
Notice the inversion of the dependencies.
In the first version of the code, the dependencies point
in the same direction as the flow of control.
But in the new version, the dependencies
oppose the flow of control.
This inversion of dependencies prevents
the system from rotting
because it stops the fan-out of the
copy module from growing.
The copy module doesn't need to be modified,
because all of its outgoing dependencies
terminate at the File abstraction.
New devices can be added ad nauseum without
affecting the copy program one little bit.
Now consider this:
those five functions in the File data structure
are exactly equivalent to C++ vtables used
to implement virtual functions.
They're logically equivalent to the
polymorphic dispatch mechanism
used in Java, C#, Python, Ruby, Smalltalk
and every other OO language.
This means that getchar and putchar are logically
equivalent to polymorphic methods
on a class named File.
So, the new version of copy is really
an object oriented program.
This program may not look OO to you because
it's written in C, and C is not an OO language.
But that's not really important:
you don't need an OO language
to write an OO program.
All you really need to do is to invert key
dependencies by using dynamic polymorphism.
To make this point clear,
take a look at this diagram
which is the logical equivalent of
the getchar/putchar solution
and yet it's clearly an object oriented program.
File is an interface which is implemented by
the two IO drivers for the
keyboard and the printer,
and it's used by the Copy algorithm.
And here is the code.
Again, it's semantically identical to
the getchar/putchar solution,
but it's written in an OO language.
Notice the inversion of the dependencies.
The Keyboard and the Printer derivatives
of the Reader and Writer interfaces
depend in a direction that opposes
the flow of control.
What is OO?
What is "OO"?
In 1966 two Norwegian computer scientists,
Ole Johan Dahl and Kristen Nygaard,
were fiddling around with the Algol 60 compiler.
They took a critical data structure, the
function call stack frame,
and they moved it from the stack to the heap.
And OO was born. They had invented the
first OO language: Simula 67
Dahl and Nygaard invented the method call syntax
that we are so familiar with: o.f(x)
But is this syntax really the essence of OO?
Is o.f(x) really so different from f(o, x) ?
Any python programmer can tell you it's not.
Dahl and Nygaard also imbued Simula 67
with dynamic polymorphism.
This gives the statement o.f(x) an
interesting new interpretation:
The caller does not know which implementation
of f will really be invoked,
so the caller has been decoupled from
the function that gets called.
But it was Alan Kay who gave us the
most effective metaphor:
"OO is about passing messages".
When you pass a message, you lose control over
how that message is going to be interpreted.
You don't know where is it going to wind up.
You can only hope that the receiver of the
message reacts appropriately.
Thus the sender does not depend upon the recipient,
nor does the recipient depend upon the sender.
Both of them depend upon the message,
which is an abstraction.
The dependency opposes the flow of control,
and it is this that is the essence of OO.
It's often said that OO is about modeling
the real world within your software.
There's truth to this, but in fact there is nothing
special about OO that allows it:
programming is about modeling the
real world within your software.
It's often said that OO is inheritance,
encapsulation and polymorphism.
And while it's true that they're involved, you can
use inheritance, polymorphism and encapsulation
to write programs that rot every bit as well,
as that copy program rotted.
Encapsulation, inheritance and polymorphism
are mechanisms within OO,
but they're not it's essential quality.
The essential quality of OO, the thing that makes
it different from other paradigms,
and the thing that makes it useful,
is the ability to invert key dependencies,
protecting high level policies, from low level details.
In the end, OOP design is all about
dependency management.
Dependency Management
Over the years I've assembled
11 principles of object-oriented design.
Each of these principles involves an aspect
of dependency management.
Indeed, we could call them
dependency management principles.
The first five principles control the relationships
and operations between classes.
They're called the SOLID principles, because
their names form the acronym: SOLID
These five principles describe the way that classes,
in an object oriented design, relate to one anther.
They're all about the dependencies between those classes,
and the motivations for creating those dependencies.
The next three principles are called the
principles of component cohesion.
They describe the forces that cause classes to be
grouped into independently deployable components.
The last three principles are the principles
of component coupling.
These principles describe the forces that govern
the dependencies between components.
Taken together these principles form
a regime of dependency management,
which describes how we use OO to build
applications out of classes and compose them
into independently deployable components
with high cohesion and low coupling.
The next several episodes will investigate
these principles in extreme detail.
We’ll look at them from all sides, and will
investigate case studies that apply them.
Our goal is going to be to employ the principles
of object oriented design to create
software application with robust designs and
architectures that don’t smell, and don’t rot.
Conclusion
So let’s review:
In this episode we've laid the foundation
for the SOLID principles of software design
by first understanding just what software design is.
We discussed Jack Reeve’s remarkable insight that,
unlike most other industries,
software is expensive to design, but cheap to build.
We showed that this implies that software
should be designed and built iteratively
without huge up front planning.
We talked about design smells, the kinds of
things that go wrong with the design of a system.
We talked about Rigidity, Fragility, Immobility,
Viscosity, and Needless Complexity.
We watched some code rot, and we saw how
the design of that code promoted that rot.
We also learned that designs that have
an inverted dependency structure,
where the dependencies oppose the
flow of control, tend not to rot.
We discussed the history of OO, and then we created
a definition that was independent of
the more mechanical definitions of OO such as
polymorphism, encapsulation and inheritance.
In our definition, an OO design is one in which
key dependencies have been inverted
in order to isolate high level policy
from low level detail.
Finally we talked about dependency management,
and the role that the SOLID principles play
in keeping the source code dependencies in a
software application under control.
So that’s it. I hope you learned something,
I hope you had fun.
But boy do we have a lot more stuff to talk about.
We’ve got to talk about all the other design principles,
and then a whole load of design patterns,
we've got to talk a lot about practices
like continuous integration,
and remember that advanced test driven
development session I've promised to you.
You're not gonna want to miss the next
exciting Episode of Clean Code
Episode 9: The Single Responsibility Principle
Subtitles by Lucas Videla - @luke_ar